William R. "Bill" Vance papers, Inclusive: 1972-2009, undated, Bulk: 1990-2003, undated
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
William R. "Bill" Vance papers
Inclusive: 1972-2009, undated, Bulk: 1990-2003, undated
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
102
Vance, William R., 1939 -
2 document boxes 1 oversized box 2 oversized signs
The William R. “Bill” Vance papers offer a sampling of media and personal interaction with Vance during his time as justice for the 10th Court of Appeals in Waco, spanning from 1989-2009. The collection is primarily press clippings, with some correspondence, campaign materials, and administrative documents.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
William R. “Bill” Vance was born in Bryan, Texas in 1939. He received a Bachelor of Arts in Economics from Texas A&M before attending the University of Texas School of Law, from which he graduated in 1963. Having been admitted to the bar the year of his graduation, Vance worked as the Assistant District Attorney for Brazos County from 1964-1967, and as County Judge from 1967-1978. From 1978-1990, Vance engaged in private legal practice, founding his own firm in 1982. In 1990, Vance defeated incumbent Terry Means to assume a seat on the 10th Court of Appeals, the first native of Brazos County to achieve the office. He won unopposed reelection twice, additionally making an unsuccessful bid for the presiding judgeship of the Texas Court of Criminal Appeals. His last term was marked by accounts of discord and strife within the 10th Court, as Chief Justice Tom Gray became notorious for his markedly uncivil dissents. Vance retired from the court in 2009.
In addition to his court activities, Vance was active in both regional and statewide organizations. He organized and chaired the Brazos Valley Mental-Health-Mental Retardation Board of Trustees while serving as County Judge in Brazos County, and was director/chairman of the Brazos Valley Development Council. While practicing law privately, he served as a member of the State Depository Board (1982-1985) and State Finance Commission (1985-1986). He was elected president of the Bryan-College Station Chamber of Commerce in 1988 after two years as its Treasurer.
Vance married Barbara Thomas and the couple have three children: Bill Jr., Karen (Atkinson), and Brett.
Scope and Content
The William R. “Bill” Vance papers range from 1972-2009, and cover a portion of Vance’s public life as a court justice and candidate for state office. Included are a number of press clippings from throughout Vance’s career. Correspondence related to campaigns for both the 10th Court and Court of Criminal Appeals, as well as some correspondence from Vance’s time on the 10th Court, provide additional context for some of the clippings. Also enclosed are several awards and honors Vance earned over the course of his career.
The 1990 campaign was not particularly ideologically driven and focused instead on the disparity between the qualifications of the two candidates. In contrast, Vance’s 2000 campaign was framed heavily around broader discussions of the state of the American justice system. The clippings and letters in the collection display the negative view Texas media held toward the Court of Criminal Appeals, characterizing it as a partisan body so obsessed with “law and order” that it ignored evidence that might exonerate (or at least demand a new trial for) its appellants. Of particular interest are the campaigns’ existence in the context of debates surrounding the usefulness of DNA testing for overturning convictions (the Roy Criner case, in which the CCA explicitly ignored DNA evidence, is mentioned multiple times). Vance’s opponent, Sharon Keller, was indicted as the ringleader and mouthpiece for this unsympathetic court.
Vance’s time in court was mostly productive, and his statements to the press consistently emphasize his ability to work through his assigned caseloads. However, with the ascension of Tom Gray to the position of chief justice in 2003, tensions began to show in the court’s internal workings. Gray was consistently critical of the number of cases being overturned by the court, noting that a number of these overturned cases were also being overturned by higher courts. His dissenting opinions took jabs at the other sitting justices, eventually drawing significant attention from the popular press.
Arrangement
The William R. “Bill” Vance papers were received in 2018. They were arranged in no apparent order.
The papers are arranged first by primary correspondents and then chronologically. There are three series: I. General, II. Campaigns, III. 10th Court of Appeals.
Series II, Campaigns, has two subseries: I. 10th Court of Appeals, II. Texas Court of Criminal Appeals.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 102. Acquired 2018-08-16
Related Resources
Related references
William R. “Bill” Vance papers, Accession #102, Box 1, Folder 12, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W.R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
William R. “Bill” Vance papers, Accession #102, Box 2, Folder 3, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W.R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Texas.--Court of Appeals (10th).; Texas.--Court of Criminal Appeals.
Subjects
DNA fingerprinting -- Texas.; Judges -- Selection and appointment.; Judges -- Texas -- McLennan County.; Justice, Administration of.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Records (Documents)
- General, 1972-1978, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The General series contains a pair of articles related to the “Outstanding Young Man” competition in the 1970s. Also included are a mention of the 4th Annual Memorial Day and a calendar ad for Vance’s campaign to become district judge.
  - Outstanding Young Man Competition, Memorial Day Clipping, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - County Judge Calendar Ad, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Campaigns, 1989-2003, undated; 2
  The Campaign series is composed of campaign materials for Vance’s 1990 run for the 10th Court of Appeals and the campaign for the presiding judgeship of the Texas Court of Criminal Appeals in 2000. Most of the series consists of clippings related to the two campaigns, though a few examples of official campaign-related materials (including 3-D artifacts) and campaign correspondence are also included.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - 10th Court of Appeals, 1989-2003, undated; 1
    - Campaign Announcements, 1989-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Campaign Materials, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Materials, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Oversize Poster, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photos, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1990 Election Press, 1989-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1989-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Texas Court of Criminal Appeals, 2000, undated; 2
    - Fundraiser Invitations/General Campaign Materials, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Campaign Materials, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Photos, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper Ads, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Print Voter Guides, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Materials Sent to Newspapers, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Editorial Endorsements, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Anti-Keller Articles, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General Campaign Articles, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Campaign Correspondence, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 10th Court of Appeals, 1990-2009, undated; 3
  The 10th Court of Appeals series is composed of documents related to Vance’s time as a justice. Most of the series is press clippings ranging in topic from Vance’s first term to his acrimonious relationship with Tom Gray and subsequent retirement, though an assortment of correspondence and official documents is also included.
  - Election Certificates and Oath of Office, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Swearing-in Speech and Program, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Swearing-in Clippings, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Appearances, Events, and Conventions, 1991-2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Board of Trial Advocates Waco Chapter Charter, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Court Nameplates, undated (Box 3)
  - General Court-related Clippings, 1993-circa 2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Court Cases/Court Visits, 1991-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personnel Lists, 1995-2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Court History and Lines of Succession, 2004, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Vance/Gray Discord Clippings, 1/2, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Vance/Gray Discord Clippings, 2/2, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Final Term and Retirement Clippings, 2003-2009 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Former Staff List, circa 2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Honors/Awards, 1995-2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Judicial Committee on Information Technology Certificate, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1991-2007, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)